<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>articles</title>
    <link>https://klingt.net/articles</link>
    <description></description>
    <managingEditor> (Andreas Linz)</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 13:38:22 +0000</pubDate>
    <item>
      <title>AMD Ryzen random reboots under Linux when in idle</title>
      <link>https://klingt.net/articles/amd-ryzen-random-reboots-under-linux-when-in-idle.html</link>
      <description>This post describes how to prevent random reboots for AMD Ryzen based Linux systems in idle state that use XMP memory profiles.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">

<head>
  <meta charset="utf-8">
  <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0">
  
  <meta name="description" content="This post describes how to prevent random reboots for AMD Ryzen based Linux systems in idle state that use XMP memory profiles.">
  
  <title>AMD Ryzen random reboots under Linux when in idle</title>

  <link rel="icon" type="image/svg+xml" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo.svg'>
  <link rel="apple-touch-icon" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo-apple-touch-icon.png'>

  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraCode/fira_code.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraGO/fira_go.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/base.css' />
  
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: light)" />
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github-dark.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: dark)" />
  <script src="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/highlight.min.js"></script>
  <script defer>
    hljs.highlightAll();
  </script>
  <script type="text/javascript">new Image().src='https://nullitics.com/n.gif?u=' + encodeURI(location.href) + '&r=' + encodeURI(document.referrer) + '&d=' + screen.width;</script>
</head>

<body>
  <div class="wrapper">
    <div class="main">
      <main>
        
<h1>AMD Ryzen random reboots under Linux when in idle</h1>
<p>At the end of 2019 I decided to replace my, now 10 years old, trusty Intel i7 920 machine.
The main motivation was that the i7 was not powerful enough to drive a bunch of CPU hungry software synth, and I always wanted to have a machine that was able to handle any amount of audio plugins I throw at it.
It was still fast enough for some casual gaming or web browsing so I gave it to a friend who was looking for PC at that time.  Otherwise I would have had to throw it away, which would have made me feel a little guilty.
Anyways, AMD Ryzen was all the buzz at that time so I decided to go for that and ordered all the necessary parts.</p>
<p>Here are the relevant specs for reference:</p>
<ul>
<li>CPU: AMD Ryzen 3700X</li>
<li>Mainboard: ASUS ROG STRIX B450-I GAMING</li>
<li>Memory: 32GB Corsair DDR4 DRAM 3200MHz (part no. <code>CMK32GX4M2B3200C16</code>) <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></li>
<li>OS: Arch Linux kernel 5.14.8-arch1-1</li>
</ul>
<p>Now to the actual topic of this post that is the random reboots that the Ryzen PC showed when running in idle for some time.
I ran a stress test over night and there was no spontaneous reboot so I could rule out a faulty power supply.
Checking <code>journalctl</code> for errors did not reveal anything suspicious <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, in fact the logs just ended before the reboot without any error message.</p>
<p>There is a <a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Ryzen#Random_reboots_with_mce_events">Ryzen page on Gentoo's wiki</a> that recommends to set two kernel parameters:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>idle=nomwait</code></li>
<li>and <code>processor.max_cstate=5</code></li>
</ul>
<p>The latter one disables certain processor <a href="https://www.thomas-krenn.com/en/wiki/Processor_P-states_and_C-states#C-states">c-states</a> which are basically sleep levels a processor can reach when idling, where C0 is the active state and Cn is the <em>lowest level of activity</em> or <em>power consumption</em>.  Disabling c-states is actually wasting energy and thus not very desirable.  I then set both kernel parameters and tried the latest kernel and the LTS variant, but spontaneous reboots still occured.  For a moment I ran out of ideas and suspected that either my Ryzen CPU was defective.</p>
<p>A couple of weeks passed and after some UEFI update I had to reset BIOS settings to <em>optimized defaults</em>.  With default settings no random reboots happened anymore!  Problem solved?  Not yet.  In default settings memory is not running at full speed and Ryzen CPUs scale quite well with memory bandwidth.  Enabling the <a href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/gaming/extreme-memory-profile-xmp.html">XMP memory profile</a> is, except the a different boot order, the only thing I change from defaults.  This made me curious and after some googling I stumbled over a <a href="https://linustechtips.com/topic/1298348-ryzen-reboot-at-idle-solved-rma/">linustechtips forum thread</a> where someone suggested to disable memory <em>power down mode</em>.  Because BIOS settings are often undocumented I cannot exactly say what this settings does, except from the obviously disabling some memory power saving feature.  Anyways, this setting was located under <code>AI Tweaker -&gt; Memory Timing Controls</code> which is kind of hidden.</p>
<p>To make a long story short, disabling memory <em>power down mode</em> made the random reboots disappear, even when if the memory XMP profile is activated.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>dmidecode to the rescue, god knows which RAM I had installed: <code>$ sudo dmidecode --type memory | grep -i part</code>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p><code>$ journalctl --priority 0..3 --boot=-1</code>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>


      </main>
    </div>
  </div>
</body>

</html>
]]></content:encoded>
      <author>Andreas Linz</author>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 13:38:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GitHub Pages DNS Setup</title>
      <link>https://klingt.net/articles/github-pages-dns-setup.html</link>
      <description>In this article I describe the DNS setup for my GitHub Pages website which is served under the www subdomain and the apex or base domain.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">

<head>
  <meta charset="utf-8">
  <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0">
  
  <meta name="description" content="In this article I describe the DNS setup for my GitHub Pages website which is served under the www subdomain and the apex or base domain.">
  
  <title>GitHub Pages DNS Setup</title>

  <link rel="icon" type="image/svg+xml" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo.svg'>
  <link rel="apple-touch-icon" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo-apple-touch-icon.png'>

  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraCode/fira_code.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraGO/fira_go.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/base.css' />
  
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: light)" />
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github-dark.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: dark)" />
  <script src="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/highlight.min.js"></script>
  <script defer>
    hljs.highlightAll();
  </script>
  <script type="text/javascript">new Image().src='https://nullitics.com/n.gif?u=' + encodeURI(location.href) + '&r=' + encodeURI(document.referrer) + '&d=' + screen.width;</script>
</head>

<body>
  <div class="wrapper">
    <div class="main">
      <main>
        
<h1>GitHub Pages DNS Setup</h1>
<p>I chose <a href="https://guides.github.com/features/pages/">GitHub Pages</a> to serve <a href="https://github.com/klingtnet/klingtnet.github.io">this website</a>.  By default a GitHub Pages website is served under <code>&lt;repo&gt;.github.io</code>, which is fine but not what I wanted.  As this is a replacement for my old website I wanted it to be served under my domain <code>klingt.net</code>.</p>
<p>Fortunately, setting up a GitHub pages website is pretty easy.  Just create a repository and set the branch and directory which contains the website files in the repositories Pages settings.  <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<p><img src="/articles/github-pages-settings-source-dialog.png" alt="GitHub Pages settings source dialog"></p>
<p>Adding a custom domain is also straightforward and <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/pages/configuring-a-custom-domain-for-your-github-pages-site/about-custom-domains-and-github-pages#supported-custom-domains">GitHub's excellent documentation has you covered</a> as usual.  For my case I wanted to serve this website to be served under the <code>www</code> subdomain, that is <code>www.klingt.net</code>, and the apex or base domain <code>klingt.net</code>.  Configuring an apex domain requires an additional step which is why I decided to write this article.</p>
<p>First things first, let's start with setting up the required DNS records.  For the <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/pages/configuring-a-custom-domain-for-your-github-pages-site/about-custom-domains-and-github-pages#supported-custom-domains"><code>www</code> subdomain</a> I just needed to add a <code>CNAME</code> record that points <code>www.klingt.net</code> to <code>klingtnet.github.io</code>.  I use <code>dig</code> for debugging or showing DNS records and in the following command you will see how to retrieve a <code>CNAME</code> record for a domain:</p>
<pre><code class="language-sh">$ dig +noall +answer www.klingt.net CNAME
www.klingt.net.         3600    IN      CNAME   klingtnet.github.io.
</code></pre>
<p>If you do not have a shell available, e.g. because you're reading this article from a phone or from a Windows machine &#x1f644;, you can use online tools liks <a href="https://dns-lookup.jvns.ca">https://dns-lookup.jvns.ca</a>.</p>
<p>Setting up the <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/pages/configuring-a-custom-domain-for-your-github-pages-site/about-custom-domains-and-github-pages#using-an-apex-domain-for-your-github-pages-site">apex domain</a> is a bit more complicated because there are no <code>CNAME</code> records for this type of domain.  Instead, you can just define an <a href="https://support.dnsimple.com/articles/alias-record/"><code>ALIAS</code></a> record that—as the name suggests—alias <code>klingt.net</code> with <code>www.klingt.net</code>.  Let's do a DNS query using <code>dig</code> for the <code>ALIAS</code> record:</p>
<pre><code class="language-sh">$ dig +noall +answer klingt.net ALIAS
klingt.net.             929     IN      A       185.199.109.153
klingt.net.             929     IN      A       185.199.111.153
klingt.net.             929     IN      A       185.199.108.153
klingt.net.             929     IN      A       185.199.110.153
</code></pre>
<p>You might wonder why the <code>ALIAS</code> record is not showing up in the result.  This is perfectly fine because the name server resolves an ALIAS directly into A (IPv4) or AAAA (IPv6) records.</p>
<p>The last thing you need to do is to set the default domain under which your domain should be served, again in the Pages settings dialog of the GitHub repository:</p>
<p><img src="/articles/github-pages-settings-domain-dialog.png" alt="GitHub Pages settings domain dialog"></p>
<p>Doing this will create a <a href="https://github.com/klingtnet/klingtnet.github.io/blob/4bd965fa2772ccfc3c69bc5d22ed76d2b9fc65f0/static/CNAME"><code>CNAME</code> file</a> in the source branch that you've initially configured.  Make sure to pull the commit that created this file or manually add it to your website contents.</p>
<p>Et Voilà!  Your website should now be served under your custom domain with a valid HTTPS certificate.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Configuring the source branch and directory is something I always forget to do and then I'm wondering why my website does not show up &#x1f605;&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>


      </main>
    </div>
  </div>
</body>

</html>
]]></content:encoded>
      <author>Andreas Linz</author>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 13:38:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Touch Typing</title>
      <link>https://klingt.net/articles/learning-touch-typing.html</link>
      <description>My experience of learning how to touch type, i.e. how to write on a keyboard using 10 fingers.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">

<head>
  <meta charset="utf-8">
  <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0">
  
  <meta name="description" content="My experience of learning how to touch type, i.e. how to write on a keyboard using 10 fingers.">
  
  <title>Learning Touch Typing</title>

  <link rel="icon" type="image/svg+xml" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo.svg'>
  <link rel="apple-touch-icon" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo-apple-touch-icon.png'>

  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraCode/fira_code.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraGO/fira_go.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/base.css' />
  
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: light)" />
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github-dark.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: dark)" />
  <script src="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/highlight.min.js"></script>
  <script defer>
    hljs.highlightAll();
  </script>
  <script type="text/javascript">new Image().src='https://nullitics.com/n.gif?u=' + encodeURI(location.href) + '&r=' + encodeURI(document.referrer) + '&d=' + screen.width;</script>
</head>

<body>
  <div class="wrapper">
    <div class="main">
      <main>
        
<h1>Learning Touch Typing</h1>
<p>Lately two articles about developer productivity appeared in my news feed.  The first was <a href="https://scattered-thoughts.net/writing/speed-matters/">speed matters</a>, which is part of the great <a href="https://scattered-thoughts.net/writing/reflections-on-a-decade-of-coding/">reflections on a decade of coding</a> article series, and second is <a href="https://danluu.com/productivity-velocity/">some reasons to work on productivity and velocity</a> by Dan Luu.  Both articles stated that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Touch_typing">touch typing</a> improved their productivity.  The productivity boost was not limited to a bare increase in word per minute that one can type, instead the greater leverage comes from an increased accuracy.  Making less typing errors improves the writing flow because every typo requires a context switch in order to fix the mistake.  Jamie Brandon wrote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you compare two coders, one who can touch type and one who has to hunt and peck, the difference between them is not just down to typing speed. The hunter-and-pecker has to think about typing! This consumes attention and short-term memory that is sorely needed for thinking about the program itself.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Dan Luu  wrote this about typing speed:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I've actually looked at where my time goes and a lot of it goes to things that are canonical examples of things that you shouldn't waste time improving because people don't spend much time doing them.</p>
<p>An example of one of these, the most commonly cited bad-thing-to-optimize example that I've seen, is typing speed (when discussing this, people usually say that typing speed doesn't matter because more time is spent thinking than typing). But, when I look at where my time goes, a lot of it is spent typing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Reading both articles motivated me to give it another try.  I was satisfied with the speed of my self learned four finger typing method but what actually annoyed me was how many typing errors I made.  One thing that I can say for sure is fixing too many typing mistakes let me loose my &quot;flow&quot;.</p>
<p>Learning how to touch type takes a lot of dedication, it feels like learning an instrument or how to play the piano (even though it's quite a bit easier).  The hardest part for me was to realize that touch typing will be a lot slower than my current technique until I get more comfortable with it.  As always, learning something takes practice, practice and even more practice.</p>
<p>Learning touch typing begins with the home row, this is the middle row of your keyboard where your fingers will rest and return to after hitting any key.  For the basics I used <a href="https://www.typingtom.com/lessons">typingtom.com</a> with which I learned how to type on the home and top row after a day or two.  But the lessons were too repetitive, so they quickly became boring.  Luckily there are a bunch of alternatives from which I chose <a href="https://www.keybr.com">keybr.com</a> because it provided some nice statistics for tracking the learning progress and the lessons used random but readable and pronounceable words spit out by some word generating algorithm.  Following is the progress chart after about a week of practicing touch typing:</p>
<p><img src="touch-typing-progress.png" alt="progress of learning touch typing"></p>
<p>The green line shows typing speed in words per minute, red is the number of errors and (kind of) purple is the number of keys in the lesson.  It took me about five days to learn all characters and to get as fast, if not even a bit faster, as with my previous hunt and peck approach.  In the last quarter of the graph you can see a steep decline in typing speed and this is because I activated capitalization and symbols.  On a US QWERTY keyboard most common symbols are located on the right half, hence they must be hit with the right hand pinky.  For me, one of the hardest things was learning to type with my pinky and ring finger.</p>
<p>Now it's all about practicing and getting back to speed.  For this reason I forced myself to write this article using touch typing which went okay but could have been a bit smoother 🙄  Anyways, if you now decide to learn this skill as well I wish you all the best 💪.  It's not as hard to learn as you might think and it should only take a month of typing to become fast and accurate.</p>


      </main>
    </div>
  </div>
</body>

</html>
]]></content:encoded>
      <author>Andreas Linz</author>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 13:38:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Go Generics - A Quick Overview</title>
      <link>https://klingt.net/articles/go-generics-a-quick-overview.html</link>
      <description>In this blog post I will give a quick overview of Go Generics, i.e. what they are, how and when to use them.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">

<head>
  <meta charset="utf-8">
  <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0">
  
  <meta name="description" content="In this blog post I will give a quick overview of Go Generics, i.e. what they are, how and when to use them.">
  
  <title>Go Generics - A Quick Overview</title>

  <link rel="icon" type="image/svg+xml" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo.svg'>
  <link rel="apple-touch-icon" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo-apple-touch-icon.png'>

  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraCode/fira_code.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraGO/fira_go.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/base.css' />
  
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: light)" />
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github-dark.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: dark)" />
  <script src="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/highlight.min.js"></script>
  <script defer>
    hljs.highlightAll();
  </script>
  <script type="text/javascript">new Image().src='https://nullitics.com/n.gif?u=' + encodeURI(location.href) + '&r=' + encodeURI(document.referrer) + '&d=' + screen.width;</script>
</head>

<body>
  <div class="wrapper">
    <div class="main">
      <main>
        
<h1>Go Generics - A Quick Overview</h1>
<p>A large part of this article is based on Ian Lance Taylor's great <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nr8EpUO9jhw">Using Generics in Go</a> talk that was presented at <a href="https://opensourcelive.withgoogle.com/events/go-day-2021">Go Day 2021</a>.</p>
<p>The generics topic polarized the Go community and still does, even though not as much as it did initially.
In the meantime the acceptance for adding generics to the language has increased a lot and only a a small—but not negligible—part of the Go community is rejecting the idea.
Rarely in the last five years of Go programming has there been a situation where generics were either required or where they would have dramatically improved the readability or maintainability of my code.
Of course, there are certain things that are much easier to implement in a reusable fashion with generics.
For me this has been writing custom data structures, mostly sets and once or twice a tree, and also for utility and library code that worked with numeric types or on string and byte slices.</p>
<p>Overall, I think they will be a great addition to the language and will enable the community to provide a series of powerful, new libraries.
If you want to take a deep dive into the topic then take a look at <a href="https://golang.org/s/generics-proposal">type parameters proposal</a> which explains how generics will look like in Go 1.18, planned to be released in February 2022.</p>
<p>Now that we've talked about generics, what are they actually?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Generics let you write data-structures and functions with types specified later.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Note that this feature is sometimes referred to as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parametric_polymorphism">parametric polymorphism</a>.
Functions and types in Go 1.18+ may receive so called <em>type parameters</em> which help to <em>generalize</em> them over a set of applicable types, hence the name generics.
This might sound confusing at first but I think the following example will clarify the concept.</p>
<pre><code class="language-go">func min[T constraints.Ordered](a, b T) T {
	if a &lt; b {
		return a
	} else {
		return b
	}
}

// min(12,3) will return 3
</code></pre>
<p>You can try out the above example using <a href="https://pkg.go.dev/golang.org/dl/gotip"><code>gotip</code></a>.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>
What makes this function different from a regular Go function is the <em>type parameter list</em> <code>[T constraints.Ordered]</code>.
It looks like a normal function parameter list, but is instead enclosed in square brackets.
Each type parameter has a constraint that limits the set of actual types it can be instantiated with.
The <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/17980dff368256a0763cf042376d3fb36d06c109/src/constraints/constraints.go"><code>constraints</code> package</a> that ships with Go 1.18 will provide a set common constraints, but new ones can be defined as well (refer to the proposal if you want to know how to define them).
There is also the special <code>any</code> constraint that allows all types without restriction.</p>
<p>Type parameters are not limited to functions, they can also be applied to types.
Below you will see the implementation of a simple stack with type parameters.
A stack is a primitive first-in first-out (FIFO) data structure.</p>
<pre><code class="language-go">type Stack[T any] struct {
    elements []T
}

func NewStack[T any]() *Stack[T] {
	return &amp;Stack[T]{elements: []T{}}
}

func (s *Stack[T]) Push(val T) {
    s.elements = append(s.elements, val)
}

func (s *Stack[T]) Pop() T {
    val := s.elements[len(s.elements)-1]
    s.elements = s.elements[:len(s.elements)-1]
    return val
}
</code></pre>
<p>Following is short example that demonstrates how the stack works and how to call a function with type parameters but no arguments.</p>
<pre><code class="language-go">s := NewStack[int]()
s.Push(10)
s.Push(20)
fmt.Println(s.Pop(), s) // 20 &amp;{[10]}
fmt.Println(s.Pop(), s) // 10 &amp;{[]}
</code></pre>
<p>Type parameters lists are not limited to a single parameter of course, e.g. <code>func F[A any, B constraints.Integer](a A, b B) {}</code> is perfectly valid.</p>
<h2>When to use Generics?</h2>
<p>Ian Lance Taylor's <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nr8EpUO9jhw">talk</a> also gave some guidelines on <em>when</em> to use generics.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Start with writing plain functions, type parameters can easily be added later.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another important question that was addressed in the talk is <em>When are type parameters useful?</em></p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>[For] Functions that work on slices, maps and channels of any element type.</li>
<li>For general purpose data structures.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>The next guideline is particularly interesting because it might prevent a design failure that could lead to an cumbersome to use API:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When operating on type parameters, prefer functions over methods!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let's say your type constraint requires a method like <code>isEqual(t T) bool</code> to be defined on any applicable type.
This means that any type <code>T</code> would need to implement this method.
As you can imagine this will get inconvenient pretty fast, especially for types not defined in your package.
To illustrate this approach a function will be implemented that only adds a value to a slice if it is not already contained, just like <code>add</code> to a set works.
Any value <code>T</code> must be equatable, i.e. it must implement a <code>isEqual(T) bool</code> method.</p>
<pre><code class="language-go">func AppendIfNew[T interface{ isEqual(T) bool}](s []T, val T) []T {
    for _, x := range s {
        if x.isEqual(val) {
            return s // unchanged
        }
    }
    return append(s, val)
}

type myInt int

func (m myInt) isEqual(x myInt) bool {
	return m == x
}

// AppendIfNewBad([]myInt{1,2,3,4},5)
// will return []myInt{1,2,3,4,5}
</code></pre>
<p>Of course we could not just use an <code>[]int</code> with <code>AppendIfNewBad</code> because <code>int</code> does not implement our custom &quot;equatable&quot; interface.
So we needed to implement a custom <code>int</code> type that satisfies the interface.
Luckily there's a better way.
Instead of requiring a method on <code>T</code> let <code>AppendIfNew</code> accept a function that checks for equality.</p>
<pre><code class="language-go">func AppendIfNew[T any](s []T, val T, isEqual func(T,T) bool) []T {
    for _, x := range s {
        if isEqual(x, val) {
            return s // unchanged
        }
    }
    return append(s, val)
}

// AppendIfNew[int]([]int{1,2,3,4}, 5, func(a, b int) bool { return a == b })
// will return []int{1,2,3,4,5}
</code></pre>
<p>With the words of Ian Lance Taylor:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It's much simpler to turn a method into a function than it is to add a method to a type!</p>
</blockquote>
<h2>When not to use generics?</h2>
<p>Generics are no panacea, so it is important to consider when <em>not to use them</em>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Do not use generics when you are just calling a method on the type argument.</p>
</blockquote>
<pre><code class="language-go">func Copy[R io.Reader, W io.Writer](r R, w W) (int64, error) {
    return io.Copy(w, r)
}
</code></pre>
<p>The type parameters above are redundant and can be replaced by just accepting an <code>io.Reader</code> and <code>io.Writer</code> as shown below:</p>
<pre><code class="language-go">func Copy(r io.Reader, w io.Writer) (int64, error) {
    return io.Copy(w, r)
}
</code></pre>
<p>Two additional rules given in the talk will mark the end of the article.  I hope you learned something!</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Do not use generics when the implementation of a common method is different for each type.</li>
<li>Do not use type parameters prematurely; wait until you're about to write boilerplate code.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="http://wiki.c2.com/?PrematureOptimization">Premature optimization is the root of all evil</a>.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>it won't compile in the <a href="https://go2goplay.golang.org/">go2go</a> because it is not compatible with the accepted generics proposal.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>


      </main>
    </div>
  </div>
</body>

</html>
]]></content:encoded>
      <author>Andreas Linz</author>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 13:38:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The simplest sorting algorithm</title>
      <link>https://klingt.net/articles/the-simplest-sorting-algorithm.html</link>
      <description></description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">

<head>
  <meta charset="utf-8">
  <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0">
  
  
  <title>The simplest sorting algorithm</title>

  <link rel="icon" type="image/svg+xml" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo.svg'>
  <link rel="apple-touch-icon" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo-apple-touch-icon.png'>

  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraCode/fira_code.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraGO/fira_go.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/base.css' />
  
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: light)" />
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github-dark.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: dark)" />
  <script src="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/highlight.min.js"></script>
  <script defer>
    hljs.highlightAll();
  </script>
  <script type="text/javascript">new Image().src='https://nullitics.com/n.gif?u=' + encodeURI(location.href) + '&r=' + encodeURI(document.referrer) + '&d=' + screen.width;</script>
</head>

<body>
  <div class="wrapper">
    <div class="main">
      <main>
        
<h1>The simplest sorting algorithm</h1>
<p>Not all of us have enjoyed a formal computer science education so let's define what a sorting algorithm actually does:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A sorting algorithm takes an array and puts it elements in a certain order. What order means depends on the values stored in the array, e.g. in numerical order for numbers or lexicographic order for strings. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let's see an example, for an array <code>a = [4,2,3,1]</code>, a sorting algorithm applied to <code>a</code> will result in <code>[1,2,3,4]</code> when numerically sorted in ascending order.</p>
<p>Ok, now that we've defined what sorting means let's head over to why I am writing this article.  I discovered a paper called <em>Is this the simplest (and most surprising) sorting algorithm ever?</em> on <a href="https://lobste.rs/s/gh1ngc/is_this_simplest_most_surprising_sorting">lobste.rs</a> today.  Sorting algorithms are often used in basic computer science lectures to teach algorithms. The first algorithm students encounter is very often <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bubble_sort">Bubble sort</a>.</p>
<p>Bubble sort is by no means a complicated algorithm as you can see in the prototypical Go implementation below:</p>
<pre><code class="language-go">xs := []int{4, 2, 6, 10, 3, -1}

for {
    swapped := false
    for i := 1; i &lt; len(xs); i++ {
        if xs[i-1] &gt; xs[i] {
            xs[i-1], xs[i] = xs[i], xs[i-1]
            swapped = true
        }
    }
    if !swapped {
        break
    }
}
fmt.Println(xs) // prints [-1 2 3 4 6 10]
</code></pre>
<p>You can play with the implementation in the <a href="https://play.golang.org/p/wlTPJe7B5Ij">Go playground</a>.  It just iterates over the array until there is no element to swap anymore.  The only complicated thing is to keep around the state if two elements got swapped.</p>
<p>To my surprise the <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.01111.pdf">paper</a> mentioned above is describing an even more straightforward way to sort an array:</p>
<pre><code class="language-go">xs := []int{4, 2, 6, 10, 3, -1}
for i := 0; i &lt; len(xs); i++ {
  for j := 0; j &lt; len(xs); j++ {
    if xs[i] &lt; xs[j] {
      xs[i], xs[j] = xs[j], xs[i]
    }
  }
}
fmt.Println(xs) // prints [-1 2 3 4 6 10]
</code></pre>
<p>It does not get much simpler than this <del>and I assume that this might be the first algorithm future computer science students will encounter in their basic lessons.</del>  For me this algorithm is easier to remember than the classic bubble sort but the paper states that it is not a good candidate for an algorithm introduction.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You certainly do not want to use it as a first example to introduce
students to sorting algorithms. It is not stable, does not work well for
external sorting, cannot sort inputs arriving online, and does not benefit
from partially sorted inputs.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You can try this one out in the <a href="https://play.golang.org/p/jml6LqHApAN">Go playground</a> as well.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Take this definition with a grain of salt, I wrote this off the top of my head.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>


      </main>
    </div>
  </div>
</body>

</html>
]]></content:encoded>
      <author>Andreas Linz</author>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 13:38:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My MacBook Air M1 setup</title>
      <link>https://klingt.net/articles/my-macbook-air-m1-setup.html</link>
      <description>I recently made myself a present and bought a MacBook Air M1.  This is my first macOS machine and in this article I will let you know which productivity tools I use, what other software and how my basic configuration looks like.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">

<head>
  <meta charset="utf-8">
  <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0">
  
  <meta name="description" content="I recently made myself a present and bought a MacBook Air M1.  This is my first macOS machine and in this article I will let you know which productivity tools I use, what other software and how my basic configuration looks like.">
  
  <title>My MacBook Air M1 setup</title>

  <link rel="icon" type="image/svg+xml" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo.svg'>
  <link rel="apple-touch-icon" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo-apple-touch-icon.png'>

  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraCode/fira_code.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraGO/fira_go.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/base.css' />
  
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: light)" />
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github-dark.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: dark)" />
  <script src="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/highlight.min.js"></script>
  <script defer>
    hljs.highlightAll();
  </script>
  <script type="text/javascript">new Image().src='https://nullitics.com/n.gif?u=' + encodeURI(location.href) + '&r=' + encodeURI(document.referrer) + '&d=' + screen.width;</script>
</head>

<body>
  <div class="wrapper">
    <div class="main">
      <main>
        
<h1>Preface</h1>
<p>It was in the very early nineties when I first used a computer.  It must have been the 286 of my neighbor or the Amiga of my cousin.  A couple of years later, I think when I was in 4th grade, I got my first own computer.  A 486DX2-66 with 8 megs of RAM and a horribly slow 1GB SCSI hard drive, connected through an Adaptec ISA SCSI Controller card.  Not only was the hard drive slow as hell, maybe 1 MB/s at tops, it was also very noisy.  Annoyingly loud to be honest, like if it wrote every bit with a chisel into stone.  This machine ran MS-DOS and so I learned how to remove unnecessary drivers from <code>autoexec.bat</code>, like the mouse driver, in order to free up a couple kilobytes of RAM so that I can play DOOM or whatever.</p>
<p>Anyways, couple years later I got my first Windows PC, an AMD k6-2 with 333MHz that was equipped with the famous IBM Deskstar hard drive.  This hard disk was even noisier as my old SCSI drive while also being very unreliable, hence they were also known as IBM Deathstar.  Of course you can imagine how funny it was to ship the broken drive to IBM's service center somewhere in Great Britain, waiting for it to be returned so that I have a working PC again.  It took them over a month, or longer, to return the drive which meant that I had no computer in the meantime.  Actually, I didn't even know if they had received the drive or if it got lost in the english channel.  You just had to wait patiently in the good ol' days.  Unimaginable in today's world, people would get mad if they didn't receive an update every couple of hours.  Somehow people still knew how to be patient back then, and so was I, which meant that I had to spent my time with other things.  Internet was still something new and the time you were online could be counted in minutes a day.  This is probably one of the reasons for people being patient.  Having no smartphone meant that the ordinary folk still had an attention spans longer than a fart lasts, which means they could read a book or watch a movie without being distracted.  Hell, they even managed to meet each other to talk and have some beers (I do miss that since COVID).</p>
<p>Sorry, I was drifting away, thing is, I wanted to tell that I was a Windows user until I began to study computer science in 2010.  I slowly moved over to Linux then and used it ever since, which means I am a <del>penguin</del> Linux user for more than 9 years now<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.  However, I always missed my favorite audio software in Linux, even though it got better in recent years with Wine, <a href="https://github.com/robbert-vdh/yabridge">yabridge</a>, <a href="https://www.bitwig.com/">Bitwig</a>, and <a href="https://pipewire.org/">pipewire</a>.  Still, it isn't a lot of fun because there is so much configuration involved.  But not only that, every so often something breaks and after ten minutes fixing whatever has failed you give up and do something else, which is not music making.</p>
<p>For quite some time now I've been arguing with myself if I can justify to get a Mac and be done with it.  Some years ago this would have been a serious financial decision but now I earn enough so that I can just buy one if I want one.  This is a privilege and I'm well aware of that.  But trust me, I still know way to well what it means to have almost no spare money.</p>
<p>Maybe it's only me but computers should just work.  I happily pay the additional price if it means that I don't have to deal with bug trackers in my rare free time.  The mac solves exactly that for me.  It just works and I have (almost) the best of both worlds, all my favorite audio software as well as all the developer tools I need.  Except that docker sucks really big on Apple, but that's okay for me.  With the introduction of Apple silicon there is also less reason to keep on x86.  The M1 chips are the biggest performance impact since SSDs entered the home computer market.  I received an M1 MacBook Pro from my employee, the 2020 model not the M1 Pro, and the machine is great and almost as fast as my Ryzen 3700x desktop.  Of course, the touch bar is garbage and I understand why they ditched it with the new models.  Eventually I decided to buy myself a present and get the better and slightly cheaper alternative to the 2020 MacBook Pro, the fan-less MacBook Air.  This thing is fast, battery life feels endless it is always dead silent.  The fan in the Pro model is also off almost all of the time, but knowing that there isn't even fan inside is just mind blowing, regarding how noisy laptops commonly are.  For now I can just say that I 💚 this thing.</p>
<h1>My MacBook Air M1 Setup</h1>
<p>Here's the list of things I installed on the MacBook Air:</p>
<p>First thing I did was to install Firefox with two extensions <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/multi-account-containers/">multi-account containers</a> and <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/ublock-origin/?utm_source=addons.mozilla.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=search">ublock origin</a> of course.  It should be prohibited to use a web browser without ad blocker.</p>
<p>Now it was time to get <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a> so that I can take notes.  As for most tools I just use the default configuration, except that I have activated the daily notes extension.  This extension allows to easily create a page from a template for each day, where my template looks like this:</p>
<pre><code class="language-md"># {{date}}

- placeholder

## Tasks

- [ ] a task
</code></pre>
<p>Another indispensable tool is <a href="https://keepassxc.org/">KeePassXC</a>.  Honestly, I don't know most of my passwords and I don't care to since KeePass does that for me.</p>
<p>Having a password manager installed meant that I can lookup my Apple password to sign in into my Apple account.  Otherwise I could not install anything from the app store.  The mac app store is the same garbage as all the other ones and I think they are a bad idea.</p>
<p>Let's go on with another Mozilla tool that I use daily and this is <a href="https://www.thunderbird.net/en-US/">Thunderbird</a>.  I could use Apple Mail but there is no way to only accept text mails with this fancy app, so I just stick with the ⚡️🕊.  Once in a while I send a GPG encrypted email, which is also a no go for Apples hipster mail client.</p>
<p>What really amazed me after years of Linux desktop usage was that CalDav (calendar) and CardDav (address book) is very well integrated into the system and it took me like 30s to connect it to my <a href="https://www.fastmail.com/">Fastmail</a> account.  The calendar app is fine by the way.</p>
<p>Despite being no flat-earther I do like <a href="https://telegram.org/">Telegram</a> for it's thin desktop client.  They still know how to build a cross platform app that doesn't require to load a browser in the background.</p>
<p>Don't worry my dear reader, I also use <a href="https://signal.org/">Signal</a>, one does not rule out the other.</p>
<p>Admittedly, window management is very primitive on macOS.  I have tried tiling window managers on Linux but I didn't like them too much, probably because they required days of configuration until they were usable.  I'm simple in that regards and just wanted to have something like Aero Snap on Windows, that is tiling windows by dragging them to a screen border.  For macOS there was an app called Hookshot that was recently renamed to <a href="https://rectangleapp.com/pro">Rectangle</a>.  I payed for Rectangle App but I only use windows snapping.  Renaming an app from something easy to google to a generic term like rectangle is a questionable decision to begin with, but if you have already installed Hookshot and want to upgrade to Rectangle I recommend to uninstall it and power cycle the machine.  This is no joke, window snapping still didn't work after a reboot but after I powered the laptop on and off.  Don't ask, I would like to know as well why this was necessary (I don't refer to the renaming here 😅).</p>
<p>Another thing which annoyed me on macOS is that you cannot switch between windows of the same app using <code>&lt;cmd&gt;+&lt;tab&gt;</code>.  Some expert had the fantastic idea to hide this functionality behind <code>&lt;cmd&gt;+~</code>, hope that whoever did that is happy now.  Gnome replicated the same idiotic behavior but at least you could configure it.  Well, there is a great open source app called <a href="https://alt-tab-macos.netlify.app">alt-tab</a> for macOS which binds by default to <code>&lt;option&gt;+&lt;tab&gt;</code> and provides a sensible application switcher.</p>
<p>Time to install a code editor.  My weapon of choice is <del>GNU Emacs</del> <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/">VS Code</a>.  I try to keep the number of extensions minimal and use whatever is the default suggestion for a file type.  There is one additional setup to do on macOS that is to run <code>Shell Command: Install 'code' command in PATH</code> with <code>&lt;ctrl&gt;+P</code> so that I can start VS Code from within a terminal.</p>
<p><a href="https://go.dev/">Go</a> go go!</p>
<p>It breaks my heart but I also need to install <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/idea/">JetBrains IDEA</a> in the community edition because there still is <a href="https://github.com/klingtnet/bitwig-extensions">a Java repository I need to work on</a>.</p>
<p>I am a <a href="https://www.ibm.com/plex/">IBM Plex</a> convert and now use <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/lp/mono/">JetBrains Mono</a> as my monospace font of choice.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.spotify.com/de/">Spotify</a>, the billion dollar company that is unable to distinguish two artists with the same name.  The day I figure out how to properly handle ID3 tags with Go will be the day I cancel my Spotify subscription and remove their electron monstrosity.  Till then I will use their app and live with the limitation of 10k songs per playlist.  Oh, one additional thing, make sure to disable <em>Normalize Volume</em>, all it does is to make everything half as loud which is not what I understand of volume normalization but what do I know.</p>
<p>Once in a while I need to create or work with vector graphics and so I bought <a href="https://affinity.serif.com/en-us/designer/">Affinity Designer</a> while it was on x-mas sale two years ago.  I am by far no expert in this domain, but let me tell you, I would prefer this to Adobe Illustrator any time of the day.  Even without a discount, 55€ is more than fair for the software you get.  You could also buy a tube of <a href="https://www.supremenewyork.com/previews/fallwinter2020/accessories/supreme-colgate-toothpaste">Supreme Toothpaste</a> for that money, depends on if you already gave up or not.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/MonitorControl/MonitorControl/">MonitorControl</a> is another great piece of software.  Controlling the brightness of my external display like for the integrated one is a feature I always wanted.  For Linux there is an alternative called <a href="https://github.com/ddccontrol/ddccontrol">ddccontrol</a> but it's not as neatly integrated as MonitorControl is.</p>
<p><a href="https://rust-lang.org">Rust</a>, once my favorite programming language, is also something I use regularly, even though not as often as I should.  The language toolchain is best installed using <a href="https://rustup.rs/">rustup</a>.</p>
<p>VPN providers are often a bit shady, the one exception for me is <a href="https://mullvad.net/en/">Mullvad</a>.  They <a href="https://mullvad.net/de/blog/2017/7/13/mullvad-donates-wireguard/">support the development of Wireguard</a> and they their client is open source.  Also, they go a long way in trying to use as less data as possible from you.  What other service provider allows you to register without entering any personal information?  I know none.</p>
<h2>Shell Setup</h2>
<p>On Linux I used <a href="https://github.com/alacritty/alacritty/issues/4673">alacritty</a> as my terminal emulator of choice but they don't notarize their binaries for macOS, which I can understand somehow.  Luckily there is <a href="https://iterm2.com/">iterm2</a> which feels like a proper replacement.</p>
<p>I haven't adapted my <a href="https://github.com/klingtnet/dotfiles">dotfiles</a> repository yet and decided to start from scratch with this system.  My <code>.gitconfig</code> is rather simple:</p>
<pre><code class="language-ini">[pull]
	ff = only
[user]
	email = &lt;redacted&gt;
	name = Andreas Linz
	signingkey = &lt;redacted&gt;
[core]
	editor = vim

[alias]
	p = push
	co = checkout
	s = status
	c = commit
	a = add
	hash = rev-parse HEAD
	todos = ! git diff --name-only &quot;$1&quot; | xargs rg --no-heading --trim TODO
[init]
	defaultBranch = master

[url &quot;git@github.com:&quot;]
	  insteadOf = gh:
[commit]
	gpgsign = true
</code></pre>
<p>Coming from Linux the thing I miss most is a package manager, especially when you're used to something like <code>pacman</code> from Arch Linux.  The situation on macOS is not as bad as on Windows but at least we have <a href="https://brew.sh/">homebrew</a> and <a href="https://www.macports.org/">MacPorts</a>.  I went with homebrew because that's what everyone is using and despite its terminology where everything is named after thins in a brewery or bar.  Since GUI applications usually come with an auto updater I decided to only install CLI tools and libraries with <code>brew</code>.</p>
<p>With the URL rewrite from above's gitconfig I can easily clone repositories from GitHub by doing <code>git clone gh:org/repo</code>.  But there is <a href="https://github.com/cli/cli">GitHub CLI</a> that can do much more, like managing issues, pull requests or watch running actions.  That's the first tool I've installed using <code>brew</code>, not because I use it that often, just because it was the first tool that came to my mind.</p>
<p>Shameless plug, <a href="https://github.com/klingtnet/netdrop">netdrop</a> is a tool that proved to be helpful.  It allows me to send a pipe over my local network, or just a file.  Most of my config files were copied like that.</p>
<p>My shell setup is pretty simple since a while.  On Arch Linux is used plain bash with a minimal configuration and a custom <a href="https://github.com/klingtnet/dotfiles/tree/master/tools/rusty-prompt">Rust prompt renderer</a>.  The default shell on macOS is <code>zsh</code> so I went with that.  Instead of my own prompt renderer I now use <a href="https://starship.rs/">starship</a> which is pretty powerful out of the box and requires almost no configuration.  This is how my <code>~/.zshrc</code> looks like:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">HISTFILE=~/.zsh_history
HISTSIZE=999999999
SAVEHIST=$HISTSIZE

# setopt inc_append_history
setopt share_history
setopt hist_ignore_dups
setopt hist_ignore_space

alias ll='ls -alh'
alias cdtemp='cd $(mktemp -d)'

# autocompletion
# https://stackoverflow.com/a/58517668
autoload -Uz compinit &amp;&amp; compinit -u

# https://stackoverflow.com/a/12403798
bindkey &quot;^[[1;3C&quot; forward-word
bindkey &quot;^[[1;3D&quot; backward-word

# ... shell completions were omitted.

eval &quot;$(starship init zsh)&quot;
</code></pre>
<p>Before I switched to <a href="https://github.com/alacritty/alacritty/issues/4673">alacritty</a> I was using <a href="https://github.com/gnunn1/tilix">tilix</a> <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> because it supported terminal splitting, tabs and so on.  The reason for using alacritty was that it used the GPU for rendering and was much smoother.  The downside of alacritty is that it has almost no features (which some might see as a feature itself).  However, I now needed a terminal multiplexer and there is one obvious choice, that is <code>tmux</code>.  Learning tmux was pretty easy since I only needed to know a couple of keyboard shortcuts and it allowed me to use terminal multiplexing independently from the terminal emulator.  That's the reason I continue using it, even though <code>iterm</code> supports terminal multiplexing as well.</p>
<p>With the advent of Rust and Go a couple of modern alternatives for common shell tools came along.  One of those is <a href="https://github.com/BurntSushi/ripgrep">ripgrep</a>, a replacement for <code>grep</code>, that is pretty fast also quite ergonomic since I save two characters each time I've to <em>grep</em> for something.  Every time I used <code>find</code> I wondered if this tool was implemented in complete isolation because it CLI just feels weird, e.g. the single dash flags like <code>-name</code> and that the path to search in is the first argument, even before the flags.  An alternative is <code>fd</code>, which comes with an easy to use CLI and should provide all the features of <code>find</code>.  I didn't miss anything at least.  There is one more tool I want to tell you about and this is <a href="https://github.com/junegunn/fzf">fzf</a>.  A fuzzy search tool that I mainly use to reverse search in my <code>zsh</code> history.</p>
<p>We are not finished here, so stay with me for two essential tools in my setup, [pandoc] and <a href="https://imagemagick.org/index.php">imagemagick</a>.  Whenever you need to convert from some document format into another, e.g. from <code>.md</code> into <code>.docx</code>, <code>pandoc</code> has you covered.  You can also mix document formats, it was a great relief to write <a href="https://github.com/klingtnet/master-thesis">my masters thesis</a> in Markdown with some inline LaTeX here and there and let pandoc deal with the conversion into the obnoxious LaTeX syntax.  ImageMagick 🧙🏻‍♂️ comes into play when I need to convert between image file formats or I need to resize a picture.  Great tool but let me give you a tip, never expose it (or ghostscript) to the internet.  I heard the people do that, sigh.</p>
<p>The end is near, not of the world but of this article.  I am stubborn and refuse to deal with git integrations of any editor or IDE, instead I rebase, cherry-pick, commit and whatnot in the shell.  For this I need a proper editor and the obvious choice is <del>Emacs</del> vim, of course.  The older I get the more my configuration files are converging into standard settings.  My <code>.vim/vimrc</code> is only a couple of lines long:</p>
<pre><code class="language-viml">&quot; :help vimrc
&quot; :options
&quot; to unset use :no&lt;option&gt;
syntax on
set number		&quot; set line numbers
set cursorline		&quot; highlight line of cursor
set smartindent
set ttyfast		&quot; indicate fast TTY connection, should improve scrolling behavior
set hlsearch		&quot; highlight last searched word
set spell		&quot; enable spellcheck
set ruler		&quot; show cursor position in status line
set t_Co=256
filetype plugin on
filetype indent on
colorscheme gruvbox
</code></pre>
<p>I hope that was self explanatory.  A pleasant surprise was that <code>vim</code> has its own package manager since version 8.0<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.  This means that plugin installation is dead easy now, just create a folder like <code>~/.vim/pack/personal/start</code> and clone all the plugins you need below the <code>start</code> directory.  In my case those plugins are:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dense-analysis/ale">ale</a> for language server protocol support</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/kien/ctrlp.vim">ctrlp</a> to (fuzzy) find files</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/vim-airline/vim-airline">vim-airline</a> for a nice status bar</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-surround">vim-surround</a> to easily wrap strings in quotes</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/morhetz/gruvbox">gruvbox</a> for some eye candy</li>
</ul>
<p>The last thing I did was to setup GPG (PGP?).  I haven't used <a href="https://sequoia-pgp.org/">sequoia</a> yet but I do hope that it comes with a sensible interface, in contrast to GPG.  Every time my key, and its subkeys, is about to expire I need to lookup how I can renew it.  Each time I do wonder why I need to <em>expire</em> the key to renew it.  Anyways, I do sign my git commits and once in a while send and receive encrypted email, hence I need to live with GPGs peculiarities.  For <a href="https://www.thunderbird.net/en-US/">Thunderbird</a> I needed to export my private key into a file, otherwise it couldn't import.  Exporting a private key can be done with:</p>
<pre><code class="language-sh">$ gpg --output private.pgp --armor --export-secret-key &lt;fingerprint&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>Make sure to delete the file afterwards.  A bit more complicated was to setup commit signing.  I found a bunch of articles that describe how to achieve that on macOS but they all had some problems so I will share my setup instructions below:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">$ brew install gnupg pinentry-mac
$ git config --global user.signingkey &lt;fingerprint&gt;
$ git config --global commit.gpgsign true
$ grep pinentry-program ~/.gnupg/gpg-agent.conf
pinentry-program /opt/homebrew/bin/pinentry-mac
$ gpgconf --kill gpg-agent
</code></pre>
<h2>Audio Applications</h2>
<p>I will tell you more about my audio software setup in part 2 of this article, the article is already long enough.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Time flies.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Also the only popular D application I know.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>You can find the documentation by running <code>:help packages</code> in vim.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>


      </main>
    </div>
  </div>
</body>

</html>
]]></content:encoded>
      <author>Andreas Linz</author>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 13:38:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to delete unreachable commits on GitHub</title>
      <link>https://klingt.net/articles/how-to-delete-unreachable-commits-on-github.html</link>
      <description>GitHub&#39;s search revealed a file in one of my repositories that should not have been published.  The file was part of a commit that was unreachable or free-standing, meaning it was not part of any branch.  In this article I will describe how to find and delete such commits.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">

<head>
  <meta charset="utf-8">
  <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0">
  
  <meta name="description" content="GitHub&#39;s search revealed a file in one of my repositories that should not have been published.  The file was part of a commit that was unreachable or free-standing, meaning it was not part of any branch.  In this article I will describe how to find and delete such commits.">
  
  <title>How to delete unreachable commits on GitHub</title>

  <link rel="icon" type="image/svg+xml" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo.svg'>
  <link rel="apple-touch-icon" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo-apple-touch-icon.png'>

  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraCode/fira_code.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraGO/fira_go.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/base.css' />
  
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: light)" />
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github-dark.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: dark)" />
  <script src="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/highlight.min.js"></script>
  <script defer>
    hljs.highlightAll();
  </script>
  <script type="text/javascript">new Image().src='https://nullitics.com/n.gif?u=' + encodeURI(location.href) + '&r=' + encodeURI(document.referrer) + '&d=' + screen.width;</script>
</head>

<body>
  <div class="wrapper">
    <div class="main">
      <main>
        
<h1>How to delete unreachable commits on GitHub</h1>
<p>The dangling<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> <a href="https://github.com/klingtnet/klingtnet.github.io/blob/b2444ca54c74a7c9dde6504cf028b6c0f4729d8f/content/resume.md#L3">commit</a> shown in the screenshot below should have never been on GitHub, at least not publicly visible.  The commit was part of a branch called <code>draft</code> that I pushed to the repository when it was still private.  If I am not mistaken then I removed the file, squashed and merged the <code>draft</code> branch into <code>master</code>, deleted the branch and then pushed it onto GitHub.  After making sure that branch <code>draft</code> was gone on GitHub I made the repository public.</p>
<p><img src="unreachable-commit.png" alt="unreachable commit"></p>
<p>As you can clearly see the commit is still there, and I only discovered this by accident when using GitHub's search.  So, the question is now how to delete this commit?  I cannot even reach the commit from my local repository:</p>
<pre><code class="language-shell">$ git show b2444ca54c74a7c9dde6504cf028b6c0f4729d8f
fatal: bad object b2444ca54c74a7c9dde6504cf028b6c0f4729d8f
</code></pre>
<p>Its parent commit is reachable though:</p>
<pre><code class="language-shell">$ git show 01aea0c8e1bdceb7869403814a4ebb87e25883b2
commit 01aea0c8e1bdceb7869403814a4ebb87e25883b2
Author: Andreas Linz &lt;klingt.net@gmail.com&gt;
Date:   Sun Jul 25 16:18:10 2021 +0200

    Initial commit
</code></pre>
<p>If the commit would still be part of my local repository I could have removed it with this call and subsequent <code>git push</code>.</p>
<pre><code class="language-shell">$ git reflog expire --expire-unreachable=all
</code></pre>
<p>But, nothing happens since the commit is not in my local repository.  What to do now 🤔?  As far as I see there is nothing I can do locally and cloning the repository will also omit the commit I want to delete.  GitHub must trigger the garbage collection for this repository so I <a href="https://support.github.com/ticket/">opened a ticket</a> with them.  What really amazed me was how fast they responded, after 10 minutes everything was done and that's for a free account!  Here's what they wrote in the response:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As you mentioned, it does indeed appear to be an an unreferenced commit dangling in our cache. I went ahead and performed the garbage collection and cache clearance operations for the repository klingtnet/klingtnet.github.io. Attempting to access the commit directly now returns a 404.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Luckily the commit contained no secrets, but what I learned from this lesson is that I need to double or triple check the contents of my repository before making it public on GitHub.  A simple deletion of a branch might not be sufficient.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Dangling, free-standing, unreachable or unreferenced, all terms fit here.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>


      </main>
    </div>
  </div>
</body>

</html>
]]></content:encoded>
      <author>Andreas Linz</author>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 13:38:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(Almost) 30 Best Albums of 2021</title>
      <link>https://klingt.net/articles/almost-30-best-albums-of-2021.html</link>
      <description>A list of my favorite albums that were (mostly) released in 2021.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">

<head>
  <meta charset="utf-8">
  <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0">
  
  <meta name="description" content="A list of my favorite albums that were (mostly) released in 2021.">
  
  <title>(Almost) 30 Best Albums of 2021</title>

  <link rel="icon" type="image/svg+xml" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo.svg'>
  <link rel="apple-touch-icon" href='https://klingt.net/assets/logo-apple-touch-icon.png'>

  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraCode/fira_code.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/fonts/FiraGO/fira_go.css' />
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href='https://klingt.net/assets/base.css' />
  
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: light)" />
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/styles/github-dark.min.css"
    media="screen and (prefers-color-scheme: dark)" />
  <script src="//unpkg.com/@highlightjs/cdn-assets@11.0.1/highlight.min.js"></script>
  <script defer>
    hljs.highlightAll();
  </script>
  <script type="text/javascript">new Image().src='https://nullitics.com/n.gif?u=' + encodeURI(location.href) + '&r=' + encodeURI(document.referrer) + '&d=' + screen.width;</script>
</head>

<body>
  <div class="wrapper">
    <div class="main">
      <main>
        
<h1>(Almost 30) Best Albums of 2021</h1>
<p>Without further ado I admit being a music junkie.  I love discovering new music in my journey through online record stores or whenever I am in one of the local record shops.  One of the positive side effects of Covid was that people had more time listening to music and started buying records.  Vinyl sales were already on the rise over the past years, but the last two years has given them an extra boost that lead to new record stores popping up in Leipzig and elsewhere.</p>
<p>Stop buying crap, support your favorite artists instead!</p>
<h2>Roy Montgomery — 40th Anniversary 2021 LP Series</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a1654242133_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Roy Montgomery - 40th Anniversary 2021 LP Series"></p>
<p>Roy Montgomery.  <a href="https://grouper.bandcamp.com/">Grouper</a>'s 2009 <a href="https://www.discogs.com/master/214067-Roy-Montgomery-Grouper-Roy-Montgomery-Grouper">split EP</a> introduced me to the music of the New Zealand based guitarist and it also spawned my love for drone and ambient music.  I cannot exactly say what makes me love his music so much, but somehow the layered guitar tunes together with the ethereal reverb in the background create an atmosphere that makes me comfy, and which reminds of warm and sunny summer days that I spent in the country side (or that I just imagined while daydreaming).  For me it's just the perfect music to relax and drift away with my thoughts.</p>
<p>When <a href="https://www.grapefruitrecordclub.com/">Grapefruit Record Club</a> announced the 40th anniversary LP series I haven't given it a second thought and pre-ordered the vinyls the same day, planning to make myself a little christmas present.  But, shipping was delayed to January 2022 because of an unprecedented backup at pressing plants (<a href="https://www.vox.com/the-goods/2021/11/22/22797290/adele-vinyl-record-supply-chain-delays">damn you Adele!</a>).</p>
<p>Roy Montgomery might be best known for his work with Dadamah, an experimental rock/shoegaze group where he sang and played guitar.  Their sole album, <em>This is Not a Dream</em>, contains two tracks that still give me goosebumps whenever I listen to them, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MpwKdaPCcII&amp;t=592s">Too Hot to Dry</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MpwKdaPCcII&amp;t=1714s">High Tension House</a>.  His music is melancholic while being still positive, hard to describe.  This tension might be the reason I'm so fascinated by it.</p>
<p>In an interview, I read about him, he said that he is a self-taught guitarist. This gives me hope that I can sometimes create similar atmospheres on my guitar.  One of my new year's resolutions is to finally take guitar lessons, no excuses anymore.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=2966139599/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://grapefruit1.bandcamp.com/album/roy-montgomery-40th-anniversary-2021-lp-series">Roy Montgomery 40th Anniversary 2021 LP Series by Roy Montgomery</a></iframe>
<h2>Skee Mask — Pool</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a2320122722_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Skee Mask - Pool"></p>
<p>Another good year for Ilian Tape, a <a href="https://taz.de/Muenchner-Technolabel-Ilian-Tape/!5654614/">munich based techno label managed by the Zenker brothers</a> who are best known for their minimal techno releases.  This is not the first album of Skee Mask but a massive one, with more than one hundred minutes of listening time.  There are no fillers on this record, every track is worth a listen.  I would describe the album as a mixture of low-speed drum and bass, breakbeat and deep techno (it's okay to disagree with that, genre borders are fluid).  Not a record to listen on your kitchen radio though, this needs some headphones or speakers capable of producing a massive amount of low end.  Highly recommended record and maybe a future classic.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=222624053/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://iliantape.bandcamp.com/album/itlp09-pool">ITLP09 - Pool by Skee Mask</a></iframe>
<h2>Woulg - Bubblegum</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a3596139616_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Woulg - Bubblegum"></p>
<p>An album for the open minded electronic music lovers.  A potpourri of glitched, broken up and detuned samples sprinkled on top of blazing fast, metallic breaks with deep and earth shattering bass drums every once in a while.  Woulg is not only a talented IDM or breakcore producer, he also shows some of his producing techniques on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/woulg">YouTube</a>.  He released his first record on the infamous <a href="https://www.discogs.com/label/55101-illphabetik?page=2">illphabetik</a> breakcore netlabel, home of <a href="https://archive.org/details/ill030">Lisbent</a>.</p>
<p>The album cover should leave no doubt that this is nothing for the faint-hearted.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=4125215390/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://woulg.bandcamp.com/album/bubblegum">Bubblegum by woulg</a></iframe>
<h2>Dean McPhee - Witch's Ladder</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a0181296910_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Dean McPhee - Witch's Ladder"></p>
<p>Over to something completely different to the above (and below) albums.  Dean McPhee, a UK based solo ambient and folk guitarist which I discovered through his previous record called <a href="https://deanmcphee.bandcamp.com/album/four-stones">Four Stones</a>.  Witch's Ladder is inspired by folklore, mysticism and the beautiful, wide open and lonely landscapes of northern England.</p>
<p>An album best listened to on a quiet evening with a wood fire or while watching the world fly by through a train window.  Enjoy.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3681494736/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://deanmcphee.bandcamp.com/album/witchs-ladder">Witch&#39;s Ladder by Dean McPhee</a></iframe>
<h2>Stazma the Junglechrist</h2>
<h3>Stazma — Leftovers</h3>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a0248618665_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Stazma - Leftovers"></p>
<p>Stazma's leftovers are better than some other's best productions.  I have a soft spot for blazing breakcore beats, especially when they incorporate well versed rapping or funky Squarepusher'esque basslines on top.  There are dozens of excellent breakcore producers in France, <a href="https://rubymydear.bandcamp.com/">Ruby my Dear</a> or <a href="https://igorrr.bandcamp.com/">Igorrr</a> for example.  Still, Stazma is a master of his craft and shares his production techniques, like Woulg, with the rest of the world on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCOiJihb6aQyKch4FDST3niw">YouTube</a>.</p>
<p>If you haven't gotten bored by the Amen break yet, and if you like hard and fast break beats then this is something you should listen to.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=4185536392/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://stazma-the-junglechrist.bandcamp.com/album/leftovers">Leftovers by Stazma</a></iframe>
<h3>Repeat Eater — Deep Dessert Dweller</h3>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a0219005911_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Repeat Eater - Deep Desert Dweller"></p>
<p>We aren't done with Stazma yet, even though this record was released under his alter ego <em>Repeat Eater</em>.  He produces detroit style techno or electro under this moniker.  The album was inspired by Frank Herbert's Dune, a story that received a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n9xhJrPXop4">very fine movie remake</a> this year.</p>
<p>Perfect music for driving on the Autobahn or to dance alone in your living room until the clubs reopen.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=2268299090/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://touched.bandcamp.com/album/deep-desert-dweller">Deep Desert Dweller by Repeat Eater</a></iframe>
<h2>Harold Budd — Abandoned Cities</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a2697139059_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Harold Budd - Abandoned Cities"></p>
<p>Yet another album from a master of his genre.  Not a 2021 release, strictly speaking, but a re-release of Harold Budds' 1984 record <em>Abandoned Cities</em>.  This one is much darker than his other works and reminds me a bit of the early <a href="https://www.discogs.com/artist/10343-Tangerine-Dream">Tangerine Dream</a>.  Most mystery or sci-fi movies would benefit from a soundtrack like this.</p>
<p>A soundtrack for being outside on a starry night, but only if you're not afraid of the dark.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=2344114403/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://haroldbudd.bandcamp.com/album/abandoned-cities">Abandoned Cities by Harold Budd</a></iframe>
<h2>Clark — Playground in a Lake</h2>
<p><img src="https://throttleclark.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/218911-2.png" alt="Album Art of Clark - Playground in a Lake"></p>
<p>Playground in a Lake, released on <a href="https://www.deutschegrammophon.com/">Deutsche Grammophon</a>, is a special album for Clark's standards.  The record starts with a cello melody that reminds me of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xULTMMgwLuo">The Elder Scrolls: Morrowind</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> soundtrack, which has to be taken as a compliment, I really like that one.  Clark, previously producing IDM or braindance records on <a href="https://warp.net/">Warp</a>, releases a very solid contemporary classic album here, that involves all his experience, with epic sound walls, catchy melodies and mysterious vibes alike.</p>
<p>This is a record for people pretending not to like classical music but are overwhelmed by good old Hollywood soundtracks.</p>
<p><a href="https://throttleclark.com/album/playground-in-a-lake/">https://throttleclark.com/album/playground-in-a-lake/</a></p>
<h2>Tommy Guerrero — Sunshine Radio</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a1891857574_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Tommy Guerrero - Sunshine Radio"></p>
<p>The californian Tommy Guerrero, former pro skateboarder, now a professional musician is living the dream (at least I hope he does &#x1f605;).  His music is best described as a fusion of Instrumental Rock, Jazz, Funk and Downtempo<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> influenced by hot shimmering air, cacti, yucca, agaves and tequila at sundown.  Okay, that's just my mental picture of his music but I still think it gives you an idea of what to expect.</p>
<p>Hear this, or his other records, if you want to get in a good mood or if you want to relax on a hot summer evening.  Best listened to with friends, some beers and a joint &#x1f33f;.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 560px; height: 435px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/VideoEmbed?track=374561757&bgcol=333333&linkcol=0f91ff" mozallowfullscreen="1" webkitallowfullscreen="1" allowfullscreen="1" seamless></iframe>
<h2>Loscil — Clara</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a3445442629_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Loscil - Clara"></p>
<p>An ambient gem released on <a href="https://kranky.bandcamp.com/">Kranky</a>, one of the few record labels I really admire because of their consistently great output.  Loscil has a large back catalogue of great ambient albums, and this one is no different.  Sourced from a three minute record of an Hungarian twenty-two string orchestra the album has a more natural touch than ambient records produced completely inside the box, i.e. by software synths.  Nothing against software synths and artificial sounds, but sometimes sampling real instruments gives the little touch which makes a good album into a great one.</p>
<p>Perfect album to listen to on a trip to Scandinavia or Canada in autumn or winter months.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=4149141204/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://loscil.bandcamp.com/album/clara">Clara by loscil</a></iframe>
<h2>Simon Farintosh — Aphex Twin for Guitar</h2>
<p><img src="https://www.thisisclassicalguitar.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/Aphex-Twin-Guitar-Farintosh-1024x924.png" alt="Album Art of Simon Farintosh - Aphex Twin for Guitar"></p>
<p>There are not many artists that had a greater influence on my music taste and life in general than <a href="https://aphextwin.warp.net/">Aphex Twin</a>, <a href="https://autechre.warp.net/">Autechre</a> and <a href="https://venetiansnares.bandcamp.com/">Venetian Snares</a>.  I love everything they do and especially what they did.  In 2005 <em>Alarm Will Sound</em> released <a href="https://alarmwillsound.bandcamp.com/album/acoustica">Acoustica</a>, an orchestral interpretation of Aphex' early work.  No different is this record of Simon Farintosh, another UK based guitarist.</p>
<p>Listen to this if you like Aphex Twin, if not listen to it as well.  You don't have a choice.</p>
<p><a href="https://open.spotify.com/album/0mhEjBVbHDLAhwGD9ZydfY?si=HRzrCHMhRdegQ3VzXqzbVg&amp;nd=1">https://open.spotify.com/album/0mhEjBVbHDLAhwGD9ZydfY?si=HRzrCHMhRdegQ3VzXqzbVg&amp;nd=1</a></p>
<h2>Darkthrone — Eternal Hails......</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a1849020328_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Darkthrone - Eternal Hails......"></p>
<p>I do not know much about Norwegian black/heavy metal institution Darkthrone, except that I like this album.  Mainly because it's rough and primitive, both in terms of sound and atmosphere.  Nothing is worse than those hipster metal bands with their crystal clear productions and triggered base drums.  A solid black metal album must be a bit filthy, and this one is filthy enough without sounding like it was recorded in a bathroom through an 80s cassette recorder (this is the other extreme).</p>
<p>Do you hate social media as much as I do?  If so, this is the album for you.  Otherwise, just head over to Twitter and annoy like minded people with your garbage.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1173323261/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://peaceville.bandcamp.com/album/eternal-hails">Eternal Hails...... by Darkthrone</a></iframe>
<h2>VC-118A — Spiritual Machines</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a1898546476_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of VC-118A - Spiritual Machines"></p>
<p>Finland based producer VC-118A makes electro that almost counts as braindance or IDM.  Groovy beats combined with rattling percussion, spheric drones, glitchy artifacts and shimmering reverb.  An album that would even make HAL-9000 <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YjQJeMF7HM8">dance like he's selling nails</a><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Have you booked your first trip to space?  This is the album you should hear on your way into orbit.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 560px; height: 435px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/VideoEmbed?track=1434495374&bgcol=333333&linkcol=0f91ff" mozallowfullscreen="1" webkitallowfullscreen="1" allowfullscreen="1" seamless></iframe>
<h2>Savana Funk — Tindouf</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a2332196434_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Savana Funk - Tindouf"></p>
<p>Production on this record is not very great, the noise floor is loud enough that you can hear it even on speakers, let alone headphones.  However, the music easily makes up for this luxury problem.  With Tindouf Savana Funk has recorded a fantastic funk album that takes influences from north african music and feels timeless, in the sense that it could have been produced in the 70s as well.</p>
<p>This could be the soundtrack for your next trip to Algeria or Morocco, or to Italy, because that's where the band is located.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1166271148/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://savanafunk.bandcamp.com/album/tindouf">Tindouf by SAVANA FUNK</a></iframe>
<h2>Wolff Parkinson White</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.jochenrueckert.net/#wolff-parkinson-white">Jochen Rueckert</a>, a New York based Jazz Drummer, is releasing experimental electronic records with very complex rhythmic patterns and pretty uncommon melodies under his moniker <em>Wolff Parkinson White</em>.  I would label his music as breakcore or IDM.  Album descriptions of his Wolff Parkinson White records always state that <em>&quot;Jochen does not play drums on this recording&quot;</em>.  I would assume that no real human could play those drum patterns anyway &#x1f916;.</p>
<h3>Veritable Rapunzel</h3>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a1622753268_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Wolff Parkinson White - Veritable Rapunzel"></p>
<p>A Cambrian explosion of samples, thrown at you in supersonic speed and razor-sharp precision.  This last sentence is utter nonsense but I always wanted to include the <em>Cambrian explosion</em> into a review.  Anyways, Veritable Rapunzel is a chaotic mess that forces you into a sensory overload, if listened in full and twice in a row.  Just give it a listen and you will know what I mean.</p>
<p>If CPUs could dream in sleep mode this would be their soundtrack.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 560px; height: 435px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/VideoEmbed?track=3924502164&bgcol=333333&linkcol=0f91ff" mozallowfullscreen="1" webkitallowfullscreen="1" allowfullscreen="1" seamless></iframe>
<h3>Off World</h3>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a0162131558_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Wolff Parkinson White &amp; Jayden Chisholm - Off World"></p>
<p>Rueckert's second release this year.  This time featuring Hayden Chrisholm, who does vocals on this album.  The record is a bit more jazzy than <em>Veritable Rapunzel</em>, yet it still has hyper complex beats with melodic elements that sometimes feel (intentionally) out of tune.  I would say that those ultra fast polyrhythmic beats with the slightly skewed melodics are Wolff Parkinson White's signature sound.  Advanced listening material.</p>
<p>An album to impress an artsy-fartsy person whose favorite cocktail is a cosmopolitan.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 560px; height: 435px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/VideoEmbed?track=3696636598&bgcol=333333&linkcol=0f91ff" mozallowfullscreen="1" webkitallowfullscreen="1" allowfullscreen="1" seamless></iframe>
<h2>Heliochrysum — We Become Mist</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a0912067017_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Heliochrysum - We Become Mist"></p>
<p>This is the debut album of the Los Angeles based composer and sound designer duo Heliochrysum.  When hearing this album for the first time it reminded me of Blade Runner.  Production on this album is top notch, we get a great mixture of industrial like noises, massive drones, piano sounds and sometimes a heavy bass drum hit.  Everything about this album feels cinematic, which might be because <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben_Frost">Ben Frost</a> did the final mix.  I really hope that we see another album of the duo in the near future.</p>
<p>Have you watched the launch of the James Webb space telescope?  This is your album then!</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3755221744/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://heliochrysum.bandcamp.com/album/we-become-mist">We Become Mist by Heliochrysum</a></iframe>
<h2>Pessimista - Ocaso</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a0718026457_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Pessimista - Ocaso"></p>
<p>This best of list is really a roller coaster ride of musical genres.  Ocaso is a rather simple Black Metal album and in no terms perfect, but I do like its rawness combined and the punk rock influence.  My favorite track is <em>Se Ícaro soubesse o que sei agora...</em> which translates to <em>If Icarus knew what I know now...</em> if we can trust Google translate.  The record reminds me of black metal concerts in dark, shabby and smoky clubs.  Let's hope that there will be (more) concerts again in 2022.</p>
<p>Perfect album for one who sees the glass as half empty.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3120607925/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://pessimista.bandcamp.com/album/ocaso">Ocaso by Pessimista</a></iframe>
<h2>Crypt Monarch — The Necronaut</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a1170320464_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Crypt Monarch - The Necronaut"></p>
<p>This should be the first doom metal LP in the list.  Due to their bass heavy, down tuned and slow riffs listening to doom metal is almost meditative.  Of course, the more than 10 minute runtime for every track are an important factor as well.  I do like to listen to doom, be it stoner doom or whatever sub genre, while programming because it's not obtrusive and helps to concentrate on the work.  So, what makes this album special now?  I actually do not know, there's just the fact that I listened to it multiple times and that it feels very solid, sound and production wise.</p>
<p>&#x1f6b6; &#x1f3d9;&#xfe0f; &#x1f33f;</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=4231458351/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://cryptmonarch.bandcamp.com/album/the-necronaut">The Necronaut by Crypt Monarch</a></iframe>
## Tarika Blue — Self Titled
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a3851404934_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Tarika Blue - Self Titled"></p>
<p>Tarika Blue's self titled album is not a 2021 release, instead its a reissue of the record originally released in 1974.  Their music is best described as a fusion of jazz, soul and disco.  <a href="https://www.whosampled.com/sample/8049/Erykah-Badu-Didn%27t-Cha-Know-Tarika-Blue-Dreamflower/">Erykah Badu sampled</a> the track <em>Dreamflower</em> on her 2001 hit <em>Didn't Cha Know</em>.  Super smooth record, great vocals, nice guitar licks and funky drums.</p>
<p>Too good to be just a sample source for hip hop beats, give it a spin and hear for yourself.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1278846107/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://eatingstanding.bandcamp.com/album/tarika-blue">Tarika Blue by Tarika Blue</a></iframe>
<h2>Swami Lateplate — Doom Jazz</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a4055416360_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Swami Lateplate - Doom Jazz"></p>
<p>Doom Jazz is a self describing tite and tells you exactly where to put this album.  If you know <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bohren_%26_der_Club_of_Gore">Bohren &amp; der Club of Gore</a> then this sound will be familiar to you.  I really like that this albums comes without brass instruments and vocals.  It's pretty hard to find a good jazz record that is not drowned in saxophone nonsense, for some reason sax players often need to show off and give solo parts that almost sound like they're on the edge of getting a heart attack.</p>
<p>Best played on headphones while slandering through barely lit side streets on a rainy, full moon summer night.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=718302455/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://swamilateplate.bandcamp.com/album/doom-jazz">Doom Jazz by Swami Lateplate</a></iframe>
<h2>Worm — Foreverglade</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a1911764557_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Worm - Foreverglade"></p>
<p>Florida death metal outfit Worm is gifting us with a real banger on the <a href="https://listen.20buckspin.com/">20 Buck Spin</a> label<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.  Not sure how to label this album, maybe death metal or funeral doom, does not really matter anyways because the music is absolutely excellent and miles above their previous, debut album.  Let me admit that I'm the type of guy how rates an album by its cover, and let me tell you that this method works in at least <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle">four out of five cases</a>.  This is one of those four cases, I mean just look at this cover, as if M. C. Escher and Hieronymus Bosch had a frankensteinian love child (however that could be).  A no bullshit record that keeps on giving over the whole playtime, highly recommended.</p>
<p>Ever did a tour thorugh the Florida swamps?  Me neither, but if you do, take this album with you.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=713549408/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://listen.20buckspin.com/album/foreverglade">Foreverglade by Worm</a></iframe>
<h2>HunoHuno — Pleasant Valley</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a1292322732_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of HunoHuno - Pleasant Valley"></p>
<p><a href="https://detroitunderground.net/du-vhs/?v=79xpFvxFbvc">Detroit Underground</a>, a label best known for their excellent IDM and techno releases, gives us a rather hard to categorize album here.  We could just put the IDM sticker on it, but that wouldn't do the record enough justice.  A mad scientist mixture of sounds, textures and glitch hop style beats.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Pleasant Valley Detour is the first part of a musical project that seeks to interpret the mystery of the daily journey into the unknown.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Above sentence stems from the Bandcamp record description and gives me hope that there will be subsequent releases to this album.  For some reason they labeled it Pleasant Valley <em>Detour</em>, which might indicates that there will be follow ups as well.</p>
<p>Not recommended for driving (judging by its album art).</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3772356991/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://detund.bandcamp.com/album/pleasant-valley">Pleasant Valley by HunoHuno</a></iframe>
<h2>MC Solaar - Prose Combat</h2>
<p><img src="https://img.discogs.com/VrvsVa9uPArdXgNzAg4PVexWlzU=/fit-in/600x600/filters:strip_icc():format(jpeg):mode_rgb():quality(90)/discogs-images/R-20348713-1632585572-9925.jpeg.jpg" alt="Album Art of MC Solaar - Prose Combat"></p>
<p>Yet another reissue, this time a french hip hop classic originally put out in 1994 and that I managed to miss in my teenage years, much later, where I thought to have discovered everything there is rap-wise<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>.  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boom_bap">Boom bap</a> beats are totally my thing and luckily this style has seen a revival in recent years, even though mostly in the undergroud.  I just can't stand those rattling hi-hat trap beats every mumbling rapper uses nowadays, especially since they all sound the same.  No, this is not <em>old man yelling at couds</em>, I am allowed to hate things!  <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0113247/">La Haine</a>, a movie about youth life in french suburbs of the 90s, features <em>Comme Dans Un Film</em> (like in a movie) which was an outtake of Prose Combat.  A record that perfectly captures the aestehtics of the time, which makes it sound a bit dated but sometimes this is desired and must not be seen as a disadvantage.</p>
<p>No need to speak french to listen to this one, a record made for summer evenings.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.discogs.com/release/20348713-MC-Solaar-Prose-Combat">https://www.discogs.com/release/20348713-MC-Solaar-Prose-Combat</a></p>
<h2>Submotion Orchestra — Finest Hour</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a2343263499_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Submotion Orchestra - Finest Hour"></p>
<p>I am sorry for having another reissue in the list, but that's how it is.  Actually I'm not sorry at all because this album is a bloody gem and your life will be worse if you have never listened to it!  Submotion Orchestra are a seven piece band from England that are influenced by soul, dub(step), electronica and trip-hop.  I have no idea how this record, released in 2009, could fly under my radar until this year.</p>
<p>A record so versatile that it fits any time and moment, ideally the more mellow ones.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3033307561/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://submotionorchestra.bandcamp.com/album/finest-hour">Finest Hour by Submotion Orchestra</a></iframe>
<h2>Otto A Totland - Companion</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a3487084709_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Otto A Totland - Companion"></p>
<p>Already bored by Nils Frahm?  Then this could be something for you.  With <em>Companion</em> norwegian composer Otto A. Totland, one half of the legendary ambient duo <a href="https://www.discogs.com/artist/170843-Deaf-Center">Deaf Center</a>, put out an album of piano compositions recorded at Nils Frahm's Berlin studio (that brings us right back to the start).  Despite most piano records I heard this has a very positive tone, that makes it special for me.  When you're done listening to this album you can continue with Totland's previous two albums, <em>The Lost</em> and <em>Pinô</em>, both not as cheerful as this one.</p>
<p>When everything is fine listen to this album.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=2805599072/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://ottoatotland.bandcamp.com/album/companion">Companion by Otto A Totland</a></iframe>
<h2>Bleach Lab — Nothing Feels Real</h2>
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a0705886315_16.jpg" alt="Album Art of Bleach Lab - Nothing Feels Real"></p>
<p>Nothing Feels Real seems to be out of time and, without a doubt, could have been an early 90s shoegaze album.  I was really on the fence with adding this one to the list but eventually decided to put it in anyways.  No further description.</p>
<p>An album for people who like Slowdive, My Bloody Valentine or Cocteau Twins.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=907174083/size=large/bgcol=333333/linkcol=0f91ff/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://bleachlab.com/album/nothing-feels-real-ep">Nothing Feels Real EP by Bleach Lab</a></iframe>
<hr>
<p>Writing those short reviews was much fun and is something I should do more regularly, even though in smaller batches and not for almost 30 albums at a time.  Also, note that the albums were added in no particular order or relevance.  There were tons of other records I could have added but they did not fit because they either weren't released in 2021 nor reissued.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I think that's the last video game I played for hours non-stop.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Better known as Balearic. (Sorry, that was an insider joke.)&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>When did planet-mu stop releasing good music?  Everything they put out in recent years is embarrassing garbage that is just a bit to edgy to be released on Stones Throw.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>You should follow this label, they have a very solid track record of album releases.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
<p>A foolish thought, there is always some great album left to discover.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>


      </main>
    </div>
  </div>
</body>

</html>
]]></content:encoded>
      <author>Andreas Linz</author>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 13:38:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>